# GILLES LOUPPE

Academic resume

# PERSONAL INFORMATION

Born in Belgium, 26 April 1987

email g.louppe@nyu.edu

scholar F\_77d4QAAAA

orcid 0000-0002-2082-3106

github @glouppe

phone +41 (0) 77 99 53 433

## RESEARCH INTERESTS AND OBJECTIVES

As a researcher, my far ambition is to make artificial intelligence a cornerstone of the modern scientific method. Using particle physics as a testbed, my present research interests circle around how to use or design new machine learning algorithms to approach data-driven scientific problems in new and revolutionizing ways. With this goal in mind, my topics of current research include methods for simulator-based likelihood-free inference, algorithms to handle systematic uncertainties in inference models, and developments in sequential model-based optimization.

## WORK EXPERIENCE

2015–Present Postdoctoral Associate · New York University (USA), CERN (Switzerland)

Machine learning research for high energy physics.

2014–2015 Marie-Curie COFUND Research Fellow · CERN (Switzerland)

Machine learning and data analysis on text and bibliographic data.

2010–2014 F.R.S.-FNRS Research Fellow · University of Liège (Belgium)

Fundamental and applied research in machine learning and data analysis. Expertise in tree-based methods.

Teaching assistant (Introduction to Algorithmics, Data Structures and Algorithms, Machine Learning).

**EDUCATION** 

2010–2014 PhD in Computer Sciences · *University of Liège (Belgium)* 

Thesis: Understanding Random Forests – From Theory to Practice.

2008–2010 Master in Computer Sciences · *University of Liège (Belgium)* 

Thesis: Collaborative Filtering – Scalable approaches using Restricted Boltzmann Machines.

Erasmus student at the Royal Institute of Technology (KTH), Sweden. *Summa cum laude.* 

2005–2008 Bachelor in Computer Sciences · University of Liège (Belgium)

Summa cum laude.

#### **PAPERS**

- 2016 [22] Learning to Pivot with Adversarial Networks. Gilles Louppe, Michael Kagan, Kyle Cranmer. [PDF, Code]
  - [21] Experiments using machine learning to approximate likelihood ratios for mixture models. Kyle Cranmer, Juan Pavez, Gilles Louppe, W. K. Brooks. [PDF]
  - [20] Approximating Likelihood Ratios with Calibrated Discriminative Classifiers. Kyle Cranmer, Juan Pavez, Gilles Louppe. [PDF, Code]
  - [19] Random subspace with trees for feature selection under memory constraints. Antonio Sutera, Clia Chatel, Gilles Louppe, Louis Wehenkel, Pierre Geurts.

    [PDF]
  - [18] Context-dependent feature analysis with random forests. Antonio Sutera, Gilles Louppe, Vn Anh Huynh-Thu, Louis Wehenkel, Pierre Geurts. [PDF]
  - [17] Visualizatoin of Publication Impact. Eamonn Maguire, Javier Martin Montull, Gilles Louppe. [PDF, Code]
  - [16] Collaborative analysis of multi-gigapixel imaging data using Cytomine. Raphael Maree, Loic Rollus, Benjamin Stevens, Renaud Hoyoux, Gilles Louppe, Remy Vandaele, Jean-Michel Begon, Philipp Kainz, Pierre Geurts, Louis Wehenkel. [PDF, Code]
- 2015 [15] Pitfalls of evaluating a classifiers performance in high energy physics applications. Gilles Louppe, Tim Head. [Notebook]
  - [14] Ethnicity sensitive author disambiguation using semi-supervised learning. Gilles Louppe, Hussein Al-Natsheh, Mateusz Susik, Eamonn Maguire. [PDF, Code]
  - [13] Collaborative analysis of gigapixel images using Cytomine. Rmy Vandaele, Raphal Mare, Pierre Geurts, Loc Rollus, Benjamin Stvens, Renaud Hoyoux, Jean-Michel Begon, Gilles Louppe, Louis Wehenkel. Acta Stereologica, July, 2015. [PDF]
  - [12] Scikit-learn: Machine Learning Without Learning the Machinery. Gael Varoquaux, Lars Buitinck, Gilles Louppe, Olivier Grisel, Fabian Pedregosa, Andreas Mueller. GetMobile: Mobile Computing and Communications 19 (1), 29-33, 2015. [PDF]
  - [11] Solar Energy Prediction: An International Contest to Initiate Interdisciplinary Research on Compelling Meteorological Problems. Amy McGovern, David John Gagne II, Lucas Eustaquio, Gilberto Titericz Junior, Benjamin

- Lazorthes, Owen Zhang, Gilles Louppe, Peter Prettenhofer, Jeffrey Basara, Thomas Hamill, David Margolin. Bulletin of the American Meteorological Society, 2015. [PDF]
- [10] Understanding Random Forests: From Theory to Practice. Gilles Louppe. PhD thesis, University of Liège, 2010. [PDF, Code]
  - [9] Simple connectome inference from partial correlation statistics in calcium imaging. Antonio Sutera, Arnaud Joly, Vincent Francois-Lavet, Zixiao Aaron Qiu, Gilles Louppe, Damien Ernst, Pierre Geurts. [PDF, Code]
  - [8] Exploiting SNP Correlations within Random Forest for Genome-Wide Association Studies. Vincent Botta, Gilles Louppe, Pierre Geurts, Louis Wehenkel. PLoS ONE 9(4), 2014. [PDF, Code]
  - [7] A hybrid human-computer approach for large-scale image-based measurements using web services and machine learning. Raphael Marée, Loic Rollus, Benjamin Stevens, Gilles Louppe, et al. 11th IEEE International Symposium on Biomedical Imaging, Beijing, China, 2014. [PDF]
- 2013 [6] Understanding variable importances in forests of randomized trees. Gilles Louppe, Louis Wehenkel, Antonio Sutera, Pierre Geurts. NIPS, Lake Tahoe, United States, 2013. [PDF, Code]
  - [5] API design for machine learning software: experiences from the scikit-learn project. Lars Buitinck, Gilles Louppe, Mathieu Blondel, et al. ECML-PKDD 2013 Workshop: Languages for Data Mining and Machine Learning, Pragues, Czech Republic, 2013. [PDF, Code]
- [4] Ensembles on Random Patches. Gilles Louppe, Pierre Geurts. ECML-PKDD 2012, Bristol, UK, 2012. [PDF, Code]
- [3] Learning to rank with extremely randomized trees. Pierre Geurts, Gilles Louppe. JMLR: Workshop and Conference Proceedings, 14, 49-61, 2011. [PDF]
- 2010 [2] A zealous parallel gradient descent algorithm. Gilles Louppe, Pierre Geurts. Learning on Cores, Clusters and Clouds workshop, NIPS, Vancouver, Canada, 2010. [PDF, Code]
  - [1] Collaborative filtering: Scalable approaches using restricted Boltzmann machines. Gilles Louppe. Master's thesis, University of Liège, 2010. [PDF, Code]

# TALKS

- 2016 [32] Learning to Pivot with Adversarial Networks. ATLAS ML Forum, CERN, Switzerland November 17, 2016. [Materials]
  - [31] Series of Lectures on Machine Learning. Machine Learning and Data Science in Physics, Barcelona October 17-21, 2016. [Materials]
  - [30] Learning to generate with adversarial networks. US ATLAS Physics Support, Software and Computing meeting, Chicago, USA August 3, 2016. [Materials]
  - [29] Learning to generate with adversarial networks. ATLAS ML Forum, CERN, Switzerland July 21, 2016. [Materials]

- [28] Learning to generate with adversarial networks. DS @ HEP at the Simons Foundation, New York, USA July 5-7, 2016. [Materials]
- [27] Learning to generate with adversarial networks. Software Tech Forum, CERN, Switzerland June 27, 2016. [Materials]
- [26] Approximating likelihood ratios with Calibrated Classifiers. Invited lecture at the 2nd MLHEP summer school, Lund, Sweden June 22, 2016. [Materials]
- [25] Robust and Calibrated Classifiers with Scikit-Learn. Zurich ML meetup, Switzerland April 13, 2016. [Materials]
- [24] Approximating likelihood ratios with Calibrated Classifiers. ETH, Zurich, Switzerland April 13, 2016. [Materials]
- [23] Approximating likelihood ratios with Calibrated Classifiers. ATLAS ML workshop, CERN, Switzerland March 29-31, 2016. [Materials]
- [22] An introduction to Bayesian Optimization. ATLAS ML workshop, CERN, Switzerland March 29-31, 2016. [Materials]
- [21] An introduction to machine learning with Scikit-Learn. Heavy Flavour Data Mining workshop, Zurich, Switzerland February 18, 2016. [Materials]
- 2015 [20] Pitfalls of evaluating a classifiers performance in high energy physics applications. ALEPH workshop, NIPS, Montral, Canada. December 11, 2015. [Materials]
  - [19] An introduction to machine learning with Scikit-Learn. Data Science at LHC, Switzerland. November 12, 2015. [Materials]
  - [18] Classification with a control channel: Don't cheat yourself! CERN, Switzerland. October 5, 2015. [Materials]
  - [17] Scikit-Learn tutorial. AstroHack Week, New York, USA. September 30, 2015. [Materials]
  - [16] Understanding Random Forests. CERN, Switzerland. September 21, 2015. [Materials]
  - [15] An introduction to Machine Learning with Scikit-Learn. CERN, Switzerland. April 23, 2015. [Materials]
  - [14] Tree models with Scikit-Learn: Great learners with little assumptions. PyData, Paris, France. April 5, 2015. [Materials]
  - [13] Machine Learning for Author Disambiguation. CERN, Switzerland. March 3, 2015. [Materials]
- [12] Bias-variance decomposition in Random Forests. Paris Machine Learning Meetup 4 (saison 2), Paris, France. December 9, 2014. [Materials]
  - [11] Scikit-Learn in Particle Physics. Data Science Academic software: From scikit-learn and scikit-image to domain science, Paris, France. November 18, 2014.
    [Materials]
  - [10] Understanding Random Forests: From Theory to Practice. Liège, Belgium. October 9, 2014. [Materials]

- [9] Accelerating Random Forests in Scikit-Learn. EuroScipy, Cambridge, UK. August 29, 2014. [Materials]
- [8] Gradient Boosted Regression Trees in Scikit-Learn. PyData, London, UK. February 23, 2014. [Materials]
- [7] Forecasting Daily Solar Energy Production Using Robust Regression Techniques. Atlanta, USA. February 5, 2014. [Materials]
- 2013 [6] Scikit-Learn: Machine Learning in the Python ecosystem. NIPS Workshop on Machine Learning Open Source Software, Lake Tahoe, USA. December 10, 2013.
  [Materials]
  - [5] Understanding variable importances in forests of randomized trees. NIPS, Lake Tahoe, USA. December 8, 2013. [Materials]
  - [4] Scikit-Learn, or why I joined an open source software project. University of Liège, Belgium. October 30, 2013. [Materials]
- [3] Ensembles on Random Patches. ECML, Bristol, UK. September 25, 2012.
  [Materials]
- **2011** [2] Large-scale machine learning for collaborative filtering. Groupe de contact FNRS Calcul Intensif, University of Liège, Belgium. April 28, 2011.
- 2010 [1] A zealous parallel gradient descent algorithm. NIPS Workshop on Learning on Cores, Clusters and Clouds, Whistler, Canada. December 11, 2010. [Materials]

## ACADEMIC SUPERVISION

2016–Present Manoj Kumar · New York University (USA)

Junior data scientist at the Center for Data Science. Sequential model-based optimization.

2014–2015 Mateusz Susik · University of Warsaw (Poland)

CERN intern. Author disambiguation with supervised learning.

2014–2015 Hussein Al-Natsheh · University of Lyon 2 (France)

CERN intern. Author disambiguation with supervised learning.

2014–2015 Joseph Boyd · EPFL (Switzerland)

CERN intern. Text mining with Machine Learning.

## OPEN SOURCE SOFTWARE

2016-Present Scikit-Optimize · https://scikit-optimize.github.io

Founder of Scikit-Optimize, a Python library for sequential model-based optimization.

2011-Present Scikit-Learn · https://scikit-learn.org

Core developer of Scikit-Learn, a machine learning library written in Python.

# MISCELLANEOUS

Awards 2016 · Best paper award for Ethnicity sensitive author disambiguation using

semi-supervised learning at KESW'2016

2015 · AIM Prize for best PhD's thesis

2010 – 2014 · F.R.S.-FNRS research fellow scholarship

2010 · Melchior Salier Award for best Master's Thesis

2010 · Baudouin Elleboudt Award for best Master's Thesis

Languages French · Mothertongue

English · Fluent

Dutch · Basic

December 19, 2016